hi welcome back to the morning long room
or
i guess it might be evening for you and
we're in the middle of discussing
uh why bodhisattvas
are more cool than buddhas
and even if the police officers want to
go out
partying the buddhists will drive them
in the car the buddhists will drive the
car you know that's how to get a driver
uh become a bodhisattva
so then uh we're going back to the alarm
room
uh master chandra kitty says well
why why did i choose
at the beginning of my book my most
famous book on emptiness
entering the which is
wisdom underground yay uh
why did i choose at the very beginning
of the book
i didn't start talking about emptiness
i started to talk about how cool is
a bodhisattva okay and that's why we're
reading childhood kirti right now
because we are studying in this retreat
how cool is bodhichitta how cool is the
bodhisattvas
state of mind right now tonkapa
explaining chandi kirti master
chanakyuti he says
there's four reasons why
we are praising the body surface where
for a hundred dollars
who said that you weren't even here
hundred dollars for the money vacuum
thing
all right yeah at the beginning of
master channing kirch's book
why they sing the praises of
bodhisattvas
kappa says four reasons there's four
different reasons
okay here we go number one all right
uh
i gotta say this right uh
because it's so incredibly deep and
that's the picture we had
okay because it's so incredibly deep
bodhisattvas
are so incredibly deep that we have to
praise them okay what do you mean
incredibly deep
and again you keep getting in this mood
of it's good to be a nice person
it's good to do your daily practice
it's good to be sweet to all the people
in your family and all your friends
but try to imagine your mind
has the capability to be nice to
billions of people at the same time or
almost at the same time okay just
i mean if you really want to talk about
your capacity
it's hidden to you it's deep it's like
underwater and you don't really
appreciate
your capacity you know we feel stressed
if we have to take care of a few people
at home
or you know a few friends who aren't
feeling well
but your real capacity is to help
and i even hesitate to say billions you
see billions is too small
i say billions because there's no other
number right
but your heart
has the capacity to serve
infinite people at the same time okay so
don't tell me you're stressed out
because you know you have to visit two
friends who are sick and
you know and get your housework done at
the same time
and also make money okay you your
your heart is here they call uh lingua
lingua 50 bucks
word lingua i'm gonna beat you on this
one
lingua ling ling means
island right but lingua you don't know
it means uh incredibly deep
it means incredibly deep okay because so
bodhisattvas
state of mind the first reason
why chandi kirti wants to say wow let's
bow down to the crescent moon
not the full moon okay is there so
lingua
what's lingua car they can
i have i get stressed out helping five
or six people in one day
and they can help infinite people in 20
minutes
okay it's unbelievable and your mind
has this capacity you have to wake it up
you just have to wake it up
you have it already you just have to
wake it up okay
all right next paragraph we're going to
start with nippani
you guys
[Music]
should
yeah by the power it means implicitly
when we bow down to the crescent moon
implicitly we are bowing down to the
full moon okay if i keep telling you
how cool is the bodhisattva
then you understand i'm also think
buddhist might be cool
okay like if i tell you for three days
why the cause of a buddha is so sexy
then maybe
i also think buddhas are sexy okay so
the second reason
for chandra kirby to bow down
to the bodhisattvas is that
if he bows down to the junior cause of a
buddha
maybe he's also bowing down to buddhas
okay we're supposed to understand that
that's the second and there's a picture
here
okay of i guess a mountain
yeah if you're looking at i forget what
this was supposed to be
anyway oh i'm saying
this is a beautiful practice if you guys
want to try it sometimes
like here at diamond mountain
they are extraordinary views you know
you just take a walk and
it's so beautiful you know and there's a
special
practice you can do on vacation job
brady on the beach
in dominican you can
look out at the ocean and you still get
some points
by offering what you see to the buddhas
while you're sipping your
lemonade or a weight
you still get you can still make an
offering
you can try to take a vacation john
brady i know it's difficult
and and you can sit on the beach but
you can use your time by offering
the ocean that you're looking at to the
buddhas okay
all right okay third now third reason
why what
master chandra kitty bows down
to buddhist office before he talks about
emptiness
which is what he's supposed to be doing
okay why did he take this detour
why these teachers take detours all the
time
we are in a detour right now okay by the
way okay
mangy junction
[Music]
the time to take care of a tree is when
it's small when it's small the time to
take care of a tree
is when it's small once it gets started
and it's pretty strong you don't have to
worry so much about it me and veronica
planted
peach trees this year and one
cottonwood tree and you have to take
care of them
you have to take a lot of care of them
the first year and then the second year
not so much right honey that ash tree
who planted that
tree that's awesome
yeah okay so
you you have to take care of a tree when
it's small
therefore at the beginning of a book on
emptiness
we should bow down to bodhisattvas
because they're baby buddhas they are
baby buddhas
so we have to pay attention to
developing bodhisattvas aci's
first job is to develop of us
and then take care of them you know like
make sure they're okay
in the first few years after that make
them a volunteer and kill them with
overwork
okay all right
yeah self-cherishing but here they use
it for
jesus means we should
treasure the children treasure the
children
okay treasure children okay take care of
children focus on children
and then they'll grow up okay so spend
your you know
invest time in the young ones
because they're gonna grow up to be the
buddhist okay that's the third reason
why master chandi kirti talks about
bodhisattvas
at the very beginning why are we talking
about that
because pabong rinpoche quoted those
lines
and then we went on this huge detour
okay
because we don't want to finish the long
room in this lifetime yay
okay
when you take care of a bodhisattva or
in veronica in my case when you spend a
lot of attention on your
peach trees the first year it's in
anticipation of
peaches okay all right
i mean right word
in the long run what you're really
saying is
i want peaches okay why why
spend so much time paying attention to
children in the world
and why spend so much focus on
bodhisattvas instead of buddhas
it's because we see their potential we
see what they're gonna be
okay so we have to keep in mind the
peaches
and then you'll take care of the peach
trees okay yay uh
and i like to show a picture this this
this i love this picture
uh yeah that was pretty good
this one yeah uh
so this is a story i used to you know i
used to
we used to buy diamonds and gemstones
all over the world
tens of thousands every week
and one of the main suppliers is sri
lanka
which the buddhists call word
the jewel island and it really is
there's a weird thing about the soil
there
it's some kind of volcanic soil and it
creates gemstones
you get out of the car on a long drive
to do something important
on the side of the road and you can pick
up gemstones on the side of the road
it's like weird
you can still do that and
so something happens to the plants there
and
so i was there on business i went to a
place called kandi
and it's a government tree
preserve it's where they grow it's where
they have an arboretum it's a famous
arboretum okay
and they they put me in the government
guest house there
for for you know important
exporters and uh it was a cute story
as a monk it was really cool because two
things happened to me
one was um it was after noon
and i'm not supposed to eat afternoon
and
so this old man comes out of the kitchen
and he goes
and he takes me in the kitchen and he
has all these avocados and bananas and
coconuts and he and he says yo monk
right i said yeah he said oh
i got it and he put all the fruits in
the blender
and he blended them up and he turned it
upside down and it wouldn't come out
and then he added a little bit of water
and and then it
like plopped out and he said not food
water
you know you can have it for dinner you
know
then i went outside and these trees
extraordinary trees like you can can you
show the picture again
this is the base of one tree okay that
mountain behind next to the guy
is the base of one tree in candy
and in the government guest house they
have a photo
of the guys who planted this tree
there's a photo of them planting this
tree
you know and it's so high you can't see
the top there's no way you can see the
town
and the point is that
we are honoring what this will become
we are trying to imagine a tree
you know that's as big as a house at the
bottom
when we plant the seed so that's why we
honor bodhisattvas okay
all right
the fourth reason for chandekuti
to be so
excited about bodhisattvas is that
when he wrote the book he taught the
book at the
same time he was writing the book
as he was teaching people okay so
he wanted his own students
to get excited about bodhisattvas
as opposed to two other types of people
listeners and half buddhists say he he
wrote
two lines in sanskrit
four lines in tibetan uh i mean four
lines in english
about how cool is bodhisattvas
because he didn't want his students to
waste their time
doing selfish spiritual practice okay
he didn't want his own students
to waste their time just focusing on
their own happiness
okay which is the lower practitioners
lower nirvana okay
cool that's the last reason why
and then there's a picture here
he wants us to go to the top of the
mountain you know don't waste your time
with lower personal selfish
happiness you can't really be happy
unless you're taking care of other
people
so don't waste time on yourself
you know my teacher used to say why are
you doing buddhism
and then i give the standard answer
for all living beings he said you are
one of them okay don't forget
if you're gonna do your practice for all
living beings
one of those beings is you okay so
you don't have to focus on yourself
if you focus on all living beings you're
in there somewhere
okay you're going to get covered also ok
he quotes a book called ratnakutta
which means the pile of gemstones
and this is a an important part
the sutras which still exist
from ancient times okay we still have
990 sutras and tantras
that lord buddha taught which is only a
tiny part of what he taught
one of those collections of cool sutras
which is different for example from the
perfection of wisdom sutras
it's called the pile of jewels and in
one of those
sutras it says kasyapa okay this is a
section called kashapa which was a
famous disciple and also a famous buddha
bernard we bow down to the crescent moon
but we don't spend as much attention
bowing down to the full moon
okay
if you respect me the buddha is talking
if you want to respect the buddha
chaaju saba namla chaksa don't bow down
to me
go find the bodhisattva and bow down to
them it's kind of strange right
buddhists like you should respect the
crescent moon
more than you respect the full moon so i
don't want to
don't bow down to me go go try to find a
bodhisattva who's not yet a
buddha and go bow down to them go bow
down to the peach tree in the first year
take care of that then you'll get
peaches okay
got it all right
by the way uh i would say the whole
the whole praise in chandi kirti is
drawn from this sutra
okay and that's the fun thing about
al and all the gold clubs okay
we can find something from 1300 years
ago
and because we have the database we can
find the source for it
2500 years ago we can go back twice as
far
in time because of job british project
power and the other people
maria raising funds all over the world
yay
thank you thank you somebody
why do we respect crescent moons
more than full moons well because full
moons come from christmas duh
okay buddhists come from bodhisattva
station
and then from buddhists you can get
shravakas and
pratyako buddhas good
okay there's the ultimate source
obviously
for chandu kyoti okay it's an old sutra
and called the sutra of kashapa okay
cool all right
so who's wrapping up here tongkapa
what's he say did you notice the process
for the last few days
did you notice the process for the last
few days
i spent a lot of time
to prove to you that bodhisattvas are
more important than buddhist
that's called lung what's that
word scriptural authority sorry
that's logic that's clear thinking
then i went the inexpensive way
which is scriptural authority don't
believe me
don't think i'm using logic well the
buddha said so in the
kuta okay got it these are the two
traditional
ways in buddhist practice
to prove something did the buddha say it
yes does it make sense yes
okay then practice it
directly praised buddhas and self-made
buddhas
and listeners well uh
he wanted to point out what's the root
cause
of buddhism
there's no self-made but it's got it got
it
he so stop thinking of bodhisattvas
as the cause for buddhists because they
are also the indirect cause of
listeners and self-made buddhists
because they create buddhas who teach
the listeners and the suffering
okay got it so we have all these lineage
here
birth different people gave birth to
different people
then if you think about it says
there's a four step chain
of causation here there's a four-step
cause and result process here i think
alex has it now
this causes this and then this causes
this what is it
the body suffer causes buddha
but it gives birth to the listeners and
self members four
four step process power we have a
picture i think
yay four step links
it took me so long to find four
it's actually looks like five but anyway
you get the point
okay four steps four steps in the links
here
uh now
still we have to point out that the
buddha is more important in the chain
than the listeners and the self-made
buddha so let's call him
the munendra which means
the lord of the of the sages
or the lord of the quiet ones okay
uh the reason we added that the reason
why chandekiri didn't say lord buddha he
said
the king of the sages right
munendra is to indicate that of the four
that's still the most important one okay
the buddha the full buddhas
all right
but if you have to really bow down who's
most important among these four
trick question even words not gonna get
it right yay
close no stigar
yeah buddy hey you're out
you out answer the word i don't know
watch out you're getting competition
over here
okay yeah in a in the end
he's bowing down to bodhichitta isn't he
okay in the end it's not the
bodhisattvas
it's not the buddhists that come from
them it's not the listeners that come
from those buddhas
and it's not the self-made buddhists who
do a hundred eons more than the
listeners okay in the end what he's
really bowing down to
is going to a billion planets and making
a commitment
to a billion people in 20 minutes
okay and that's bodhitina okay cool
yeah the real teaching is compassion
next picture paul
yeah this is the real
this is what what's really happening in
the opening lines
of the most famous book ever written on
emptiness
it's talking about caring for other
people okay
indirectly okay yay we're ready to go to
the next
uh part europe are you with me paul
simbani
okay yeah you're good
to go
and by the way we're now finishing our
detour
we're gonna go back to this thing called
lamrim okay but the last thing
that he says the last thing some kappa
says here
it says well if we're bowing down the
bodhisattva
where did they come from okay and by the
way
that's the next important section
in chat to kitty and we're going to do
it in the next long room
okay number 38 or whatever it is we're
going to do that in the next normal okay
we're going to cover that in the next
moment
okay uh we're going to cover
uh we're going to go to the next part of
of chandi kyoti
okay where where is it that
bodhisattvas come from okay you ready
for the answer
here's chad kirti's answer which you've
never heard before
here's chanduketi center well where'd
the bodhisattvas come from
[Music]
very famous very deep something we
should go study
next lamrim ready what makes a
bodhisattva three things
okay number one compassion
caring about the trouble and the pain
of other people caring about the trouble
and pain of other people
is the first of the three causes
of a body suffering okay that's easy
right
what's the second one niso melo word
300 bucks melo
10 9 8 7
i hate you don't come here anymore no he
got it already
oh you read it off the screen get
cancelled
[Laughter]
okay
very strange to burn uh
not duality mind not duality mind it
means
emptiness the understanding of emptiness
what does duality mean in the sense of
what they call that word a uh
discrepancy
discrepancy what's a discrepancy mean
there's a discrepancy in reality
it looks like this but it seems to be
done there's a discrepancy the movement
of mercury around the sun
is there's a discrepancy which proves
the theory of relativity actually
there's there's a problem here there's a
problem here okay
new zuma okay
noticing something screwy
something's weird about reality
it's the second cause of a
bodhisattva okay that's a new one
right noticing something's not quite
right
it's the second cause of a body suffer
okay we take steps to
i don't know increase profits at work
and then they go down
and then somebody else takes the same
steps and they go up
something's going on that's called nissa
menlo okay got it
okay good all right and then change your
assembly that's easy
body chiller three causes of body suffer
okay three causes of body support number
one
notice the pain that other people are
having
number two for god's sake notice
something weird is going on
two people do the same strategy in
business
one fails one goes bankrupt one gets
rich
didn't you notice and didn't you wonder
about it
and you still want to do the strategy
you know are you crazy
okay you gotta notice that some
something's strange
something doesn't make sense okay and
then
uh and child security says
that makes your body suffer as much as
love does
okay uh noticing
something strange is going on
makes your body suffer as much as
compassion and love that's cool
okay and we're gonna study it next time
so you have to come
come back for the next long room all
right
all right
i think we have a picture for three
causes i don't even remember what it is
oh yeah okay
try the last picture
i don't know
no it must be the grass
[Laughter]
anyway let's go on sometimes girl's
tired and we can't understand why you
picked a picture
yay we're finished with the detour to
chat the kitty
and we are gonna go back to by the way
the plan this morning in arizona central
world time
is uh i'm gonna do another 10 minutes on
the alarm room
and then i'm going to do some
fundraising yay
okay by the way yesterday's
fundraising during the
fire offering we were fundraising for
guard rails so you guys
don't fall off the mountains here and
die during llama rim
in the future when you come and secondly
to fix the extraordinary dome the cat
built
it took them two years to dig the
foundation
with uh what do you call those things
jackhammers
out of the rock solid rock
she did it she was the boss and then
thirdly what was our third fundraising
thing the tractor they got
tipped over and broke because it was
overworked and the hydraulics stopped
and the brakes failed
and he went down the mountain like a
sleigh ride
anyway i'd like to announce you guys
covered it yesterday
last night okay you covered
all three which means geshe-la's gonna
fundraise more today
okay but congratulations in the whole
world you guys
did it okay yay i think you overdid it
actually but we're not gonna mention
that okay
let's go back to the thank you for that
and joe thank you for a new tractor uh
here we go back to the alarm room we're
going back to alarm room for ten minutes
uh uh shea soaked
all the beautiful things of this world
have come from
buddhas okay the previous buddhas
when was the first buna no such
thing okay
and all of those buddhas were born from
bodhisattvas charges
you give some nature and all the
bodhisattvas were born from bodhichitta
joey deiki tamche kisawa chandra some
kona inching therefore
logically that
jumping planets is the cause
for every happiness on any plant okay
jumping planet is the cause for every
single happiness
on any single planet okay
too
it means that the it means the palm or
the
or the bottom of your foot okay they're
both called
till in tibetan okay but it's an idiom
for
what you're supposed to keep in your
palm
it means your main practice it's a it's
a
it's an idiom for your main practice hey
hey hey what do you got in the palm of
your hands
which is partly the title of the book
okay
what's in your palm it means what do you
what do you hold on to all day
what's your main practice this week
bodhichitta i'm thinking about how cool
is buddhism okay
that's called okay
the palm of your deepest heart
means what's your main practice nowadays
okay
and he says bodhichitta
is the engine which drives all
tantric practice you cannot do medicine
buddha
effectively if you don't study
bodhichitta and
means it gives the energy to tantric
practice
bodhichitta is the engine inside of
tantric practice
stop bodhichitta don't study bodhichitta
i don't want to study larmium i'm doing
medicine building mantras
then the engine doesn't work the car
won't go anywhere okay
he says here sangak lakitan
kitten what makes medicine buddha so
amazing
why is it a miracle it is a miracle
if you put gasoline in the car okay
what's the gasoline
body china okay well how do you
get the gasoline you study la ram okay
then you get the gasoline then you put
it in your medicine builder car
and then your medicine builder car can
do something that nothing else can do
okay yay uh all right
uh i have a diamond here
i like this diamond i don't know
uh why uh
diamond way which is tantra uh it's
sometimes called the diamond way
okay but if you think about it
the diamond is also made from the soil
of the earth
okay it's if you if you say bodhichitta
is like the soil if you say that
love is like the soil
that grows all the food of the earth
if all happiness
of all living beings comes from love
what hap which is the earth the biochar
of the earth what happens if you take
biochar and put it in a
compression yeah but i forget what it is
per square inch but it's something
amazing
the the first uh diamond made by general
electric
i think was 1956 with the piston
compression from normal pencil carbon
the electricity required would run a
small city for a week
okay that's how much energy it takes
to squish dirt into a diamond but in the
end
the essence of a diamond is dirt
okay in the end the essence of tantra
is plain old love just compressed
okay just more powerful okay
cool all right
so should be
there was a famous uh disciple
the most famous disciple
of lord atisha who
brought basically brought buddhism to
tibet okay
and he's an interesting guy okay say
drumtonji
he was a businessman he never became a
monk
okay he built one of the first great
monasteries in tibet radhin
okay which is where tsonkapa
got the vision to write the greatest
book in tibet
marm okay all right
and he was asking somebody i heard
there's these three guys at diamond
mountain you know
yeah i i heard they're in retreat yeah
can you tell me a little bit about them
you know i i never met them
and the guy started telling the story of
cat
and then the story of guilty and in the
story of venerable jigme
long-term retreatants and diamond
mountain
and he went on for a couple hours
talking about their life history
okay of these three different
long-term retreatants and then
drumdenjay said
stop stop telling me
and the guy said why i'm not done yet he
said it's the same story
you keep telling me the same story you
know save your breath
it's the same story they're body sappers
they care about other people the details
are different the city of birth is
different
the education college is different but
he
jumped and just said cut stop stop it's
the same story you're just telling me
the same story in a different package
okay the story is they love other people
and i don't need the rest i don't need
to know what college they went to
he said just stop now you know that's
enough
okay cool life story
there's okay guess what why you keep
showing these silly pictures
because later i'm going to examine you
using the pictures i'm going to show you
the picture and say hey
what's this talk about what's life story
mean you're going to say
gesla there's three retreating long-term
retreats girls say
me venable cunning diamond
mountain who did one year two year three
year retreats
you want to know their story yeah
they love other people same story okay
that's what you're gonna say when you
see the picture okay
last thing today
then he said hey uh what's that kamlimba
guy what's he doing nowadays
you know that's another diamond
retreating i guess he said oh he's up on
the
medicine stupa top mountain
he's sitting on the side of the mountain
at the top
where we're gonna build the uh medicine
bit of stupid number eight
he's sitting up there was it stupid
there yet no honey said next week
yeah what's he doing up there well
sometimes
he just looks sad
what's he do the rest of time he's
crying
wait what's he doing up at the top of
the mountain
well half the time he's just looking sad
what's he doing the other part of the
time
oh he's crying then he then uh
drumpton j's reaction was oh finally
someone practicing dharma at diamond mom
[Laughter]
oh finally somebody practicing dharma
at diamond mountain what sitting up at
the top of the mountain
looking sad half the time and crying
half the time
we have one dharma practitioner here
because he's thinking about the world
he's thinking about the state of the
world
and and he or she is crying okay
then then atisha's main disciples
reaction was oh finally someone came
who's practicing
okay crying up on the mountain
all right we're gonna continue tomorrow
uh next class